<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://peterneugebauer.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://peterneugebauer.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-01-30T19:37:44+01:00</updated><id>https://peterneugebauer.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Peter Neugebauer’s Website</title><subtitle>Peter Neugebauer&apos;s website
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Crypto’s (ugly) killer app</title><link href="https://peterneugebauer.com/blockchain/2022/01/28/Crypto's-(ugly)-killer-app.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Crypto’s (ugly) killer app" /><published>2022-01-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2022-01-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://peterneugebauer.com/blockchain/2022/01/28/Crypto&apos;s-(ugly)-killer-app</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://peterneugebauer.com/blockchain/2022/01/28/Crypto&apos;s-(ugly)-killer-app.html">&lt;p&gt;When I wrote my blog post “On network effects of Blockchains and EVM interoperability” I proposed that it was extremely hard for a new Blockchain to catch on. While I didn’t write it, I thought that all current alternative L1s would have problems staying relevant for 2+ years, or until ETH2 finally launches and fees go down. That’s what I originally thought their use case was: lower fees and maybe faster transaction times. I could not have been more wrong. Solana and Avalanche (&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/binance-chain/bsc/issues/553&quot;&gt;and maybe BSC?&lt;/a&gt;) are here to stay. Where did I go wrong? Is multichain here to stay and was multichain inevitable? I will look at these questions from the perspective of what I call crypto’s killer app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-lil-history&quot;&gt;A lil history&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the days I joined the space in 2017 people have been talking about crypto’s “killer app”. An app powered by crypto that reaches 100M+ users would lead to mass adoption of crypto and lots of money for current bag holders. Looking back at 2017 now the Idea seems almost delusinal. In 2022 we are still lacking the necessary groundwork (cheap transaction, idiot proof wallet security, good wallet usability, etc.) to make mass adoption happen. I’d like to argue though that we already have the first “killer app” and it’s the reason why current alt-L1s are succeeding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-ugly-killer-app&quot;&gt;The (ugly) killer app&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ugly truth is that crypto’s killer app is the reason we’re all here: to make money. As glaring as this might sound it has very far reaching implications and helps explain why Solana and Avalanche are probably going to succeed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my last post, when I talked about the network effects of blockchains, I talked about them as ends-in-themselves - of course you’d want to use the DEX with the deepest liquidity for big trades - this is only partially true though, because the only reason you want the DEX with the deepest liquidity is because it helps you make the most money. Using the most decentralized blockchain is also only as valueable as the money it helps you make.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-rise-of-alt-l1s&quot;&gt;The rise of alt-L1s&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we accept that making money money is &lt;em&gt;the&lt;/em&gt; killer app we can see how this ties into the rise of alt-L1s. Newcomers also want to “be early” to projects and make big bucks so they invest in smaller and more risky coins or project. This is the whole reason BSC has the amount of users it does, people go there to buy the latest dog-money or ponzi coin. What BSC definitly helped was lower fees compared to eth, investing $200 isn’t fun when transaction fess are $60.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;do-you-want-some-vc-money&quot;&gt;Do you want some VC money?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In recent year(s) we have seen the large influx of VC money in the space. What these new projects (mainly Solana and Avalanche) have done is (i) use large parts of their VC funding as a war chest to funds devs and projects on their respective blockchain and (ii) let their VC friends help bootstrap liquidity for protocols on the network, thus starting to build network effects. These two measure serve two purposes: (i) short to mid term creating incentives for devs (grants) and users (&lt;a href=&quot;[https://medium.com/avalancheavax/avalanche-foundation-announces-180m-defi-incentive-program-d320fdfafff7](https://medium.com/avalancheavax/avalanche-foundation-announces-180m-defi-incentive-program-d320fdfafff7)&quot;&gt;incentive programs&lt;/a&gt;) and (ii) mid to long term building out the infrastructure and creating actual network effects that last once the VC cash runs out. I think this strategy will prove effective over the next few years, given that these protocols can get good dapps and projects developed on them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Users (and devs) flock where the money is, not just where the strongest network effects lie. That’s why I think they are here to stay. As long as they can provide their users with ways to make money (ie. have a widley used Smart-contract capable chain with good projects) they should be fine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;was-multichain-inevitable&quot;&gt;Was multichain inevitable?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the multichain thesis first started to prove correct a lot of people in the space we’re surprised because it seemed to go against the ideas of strong network effects people in the space had. To this day a lot of people make ETH-fees responsible for the rise of alt-L1s and while I think this is justified, from a investor point of view it would make sense to have multiple L1s. If you can equip a new L1 startup with a warchest to fund development and incentive bridging it only makes sense for people to come over and use your chain &amp;amp; develop applications. When these apps are developed people will likely stay if they have a bag in them i.e. see it as a way to make money. Because of that I’d like to argue that the multichain future -  in retrospect - was inevitable. What I and a lot of people didn’t see coming we’re the large stimulus programs these chains run, without them I think it wouldn’t be possible to grow significant in a world where ETH is fast &amp;amp; cheap.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wat-is-next-killer-app-3&quot;&gt;Wat is next killer app? :3&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question then naturally arises “what is the next ‘true’ killer app of crypto? Making money can’t be the only thing.” It doesn’t fit the narrative of crypto (at least from the outside) that we’re all just greedy investors taking each others money. After all crypto is supposed to make the world better and more decentralized not just find new ways to get rugged online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the true crypto killer app to happen a lot needs to happen first:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The UX needs to improve a looooooooooot&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Very easy (and cheap) to on and off ramp&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;basically free transactions&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;idiot proof wallet security&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;basic legal clarity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If these things get fixed then and only then a true killer app can hapen that enjoys millions of users and pushes crypto over the non-investor chasm. If we image a world where these thigns are already fixed some proposed killer apps are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;better social networks (utilizing tokens and ownership somehow uniquely)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;games (adding decentrallization &amp;amp; ownership)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;something completely different that we can’t yet imagine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;social-media-as-a-killer-app&quot;&gt;Social media as a killer app&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we have learned from the above is that crypto people might become very good at understanding and creating strong and lasting network effects, after all in a sense that’s our bread and butter. One industry where network effects are also bread and butter is the social media industry. The reason you use Whatsapp (and please insert the messenger of your choice here) is that everyone else in your social circle is using it. The same - but in a more complex structure - applies to other social media apps like instagram and twitter. You are only using them becuase all the people you follow use them and the people you follow only use them because there are so many of you (users) on said platform, good old network effects. If someone from the crypto community comes up with a cool new social media platoform and applies his knwoledge of network effects and shared ownership and maybe governance to said platform it might turn out successful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a devils advocate point of view I’d like to argue that all crypto social media platoforms so far have failed and using coins as an incentive for posting/engagement/etc. seems to be near impossible to make work in a good way; I feel like the industry is lacking one main invention to make that work, idk what that is though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;utilizing-network-effects-in-games&quot;&gt;Utilizing network effects in games&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Games are a little more tricks because the network effects are not as straight forward as for social media networks. Firstly there are only network effects for multiplayer games and even there the network effects depend more on the content of the game rather than the size of the player base. If a crypto game reaches the mainstream and attains the title “killer app” (at least long term, of cause you can literally pay people to play your game) it won’t be because of it’s strong network effects but because of the actual content of the game itself and how enjoyable it is to play with friends. For network effects through financial incentive remember: people can only take out of the system what someone else has put in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As closing thoughts I would like to add that thinking about every investment you take in crypto under the lense of “does this support the killer app ‘making money’” and not just for yourself but other people can maybe be a good guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not financial advice though. pls don’t sue if you get rekt.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blockchain" /><summary type="html">When I wrote my blog post “On network effects of Blockchains and EVM interoperability” I proposed that it was extremely hard for a new Blockchain to catch on. While I didn’t write it, I thought that all current alternative L1s would have problems staying relevant for 2+ years, or until ETH2 finally launches and fees go down. That’s what I originally thought their use case was: lower fees and maybe faster transaction times. I could not have been more wrong. Solana and Avalanche (and maybe BSC?) are here to stay. Where did I go wrong? Is multichain here to stay and was multichain inevitable? I will look at these questions from the perspective of what I call crypto’s killer app.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Network effects of Blockchains and EVM compatibility</title><link href="https://peterneugebauer.com/blockchain/2021/07/31/On-Network-effects-of-Blockchains-and-EVM-compatibility.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Network effects of Blockchains and EVM compatibility" /><published>2021-07-31T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-31T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>https://peterneugebauer.com/blockchain/2021/07/31/On-Network-effects-of-Blockchains-and-EVM-compatibility</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://peterneugebauer.com/blockchain/2021/07/31/On-Network-effects-of-Blockchains-and-EVM-compatibility.html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;update-the-author-doesnt-agree-with-everything-in-this-post-anymore-but-is-too-lazy-to-update-it&quot;&gt;Update: The author doesn’t agree with everything in this post anymore but is too lazy to update it&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every new Blockchain or crypto-ecosystem strives to grow its user base to increase its value, resilience and longevity. This has been an incredibly difficult task that only few have succeeded in (BTC, ETH), many have tried and failed (IOTA, NEO, EOS, …) and many are trying (ADA, ICP, BSC). The reason for this is obvious, establish yourself as a widely used and time tested L1 and a high market cap valuation is sure to follow. Let’s try to look at why some projects have succeeded while many have failed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;those-that-succeeded&quot;&gt;Those that succeeded&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin quite obviously (though it might not have been at the time) had the first mover advantage. For the longest time everybody who had exposure to crypto had exposure to bitcoin. As the value of a coin is also depends on the amount of “users” (or holders in bitcoins case) and bitcoin had by far the most it was a logical buy for all newcomers in an extremely volatile industry as is crypto. Because of it’s largest marketcap it was also the most resilient to attacks and had a history of stableness which certainly helped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ethereum in a sense also had a first mover advantage in being the first smart contract general purpose blockchain. It gained its first set of users on the promise of a new technology and the bet that it would one day be big. Over the years more and more Dapps got build and attracted new users as well as capital. Now there was a network effect not just on the Blockchain to use but also one around it’s ecosystem (Dapps) where ETH strived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;strong-network-effects&quot;&gt;Strong network effects&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here lies on of the bigger problems new 2.0 or 3.0 Blockchains have, in that there is no real reason to use them as a user when you get do the same on a more resilient/trusted/time-proven/liquid/exchange-supported/wallet-supported blockchain and get to do even more, as its ecosystem and projected future success (and thus Dapp-stack) is larger. Swapping your ETH to SOL is a hassle and installing a SOL wallet and using a new interface/address format/blockchain also is. With the rise of DeFi the burden to use a new Blockchain grew even larger as new chains don’t have the liquidity ETH provides nor its wide arsenal of Dapps. If ETH can successfully upgrade to 2.0 and achieve it’s thousands of transactions a second it will be very hard for other projects to take ETHs place, as they bring nothing new to the table (maybe marginally smaller fees and faster speed) and are lacking the Dapp stack and liquidity as well as establishedness ETH provides.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do you compete with Ethereum as a new Chain? There have been two ways to tackle the Problem of the missing Dapp stack: Make your Blockchain EVM compatible or don’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;evm-compatible&quot;&gt;EVM compatible&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea behind making your chain EVM compatible is giving devs the opportunity to just clone working ETH Dapps and deploying them on (i.e.) BSC, as with pancakeswap and uniswap. This gives new Chains the ability to basically have the same DeFi stack as ETH with all its research and time-testedness that went into it at basically no cost (time and money). The only thing missing then is the liquidity and actual user base of ETH to make use of all the Dapps, which will be very hard to get and maintain as you bring virtually nothing new to the table and ETH has the greater userbase/liquidity/etc.. The only thing that might keep a project from getting blatantly cloned from one chain to the other is developer pride, that they don’t just want to take another’s work as their own, I don’t think this variable is too strong though, especially when there’s a lot of money on the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;evm-incompatible&quot;&gt;EVM incompatible&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other way of competing with ETH more directly and aggressively is making your chain EVM incompatible. This gives you a much slower start, as everything as to be (re-) developed on your platform. This obviously also works the other way around. If a great new Dapp gets developed that attracts hundreds of thousands of users on your chain, cloning it on ETH is not so easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;should-you-make-your-chain-evm-compatible-or-not&quot;&gt;Should you make your Chain EVM compatible or not?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Zhu Su recently said (and I’m paraphrasing) “At this point there is no question, you have to make your chain EVM compatible”, the disadvantage of missing out on the entire DeFi stack (also of other EVM compatible chains) might overweight here. There is also the question of if clones a dapp is really cloning a dapp or just cloning the code, what I mean by that is that a dapp is very much its brand and TLV, just cloning the code doesn’t do enough to attract users, you have to build the brand and do some modifications. If you build i.e. a successful game on on SOL and its get copied to ETH it wont have the same amount of users and traction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making your Chain EVM compatible might in end be the right move, I just don’t see how you can overtake ETH as an EVM compatible Chain, maybe everybody is just fighting for #2, calling it ETH-killer seems to be quite the overstretch in that case though…&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blockchain" /><summary type="html">Update: The author doesn’t agree with everything in this post anymore but is too lazy to update it</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Decentralized content moderation system for Twitter</title><link href="https://peterneugebauer.com/blockchain/2021/03/04/Decentralized-content-moderation-system-for-Twitter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Decentralized content moderation system for Twitter" /><published>2021-03-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-03-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>https://peterneugebauer.com/blockchain/2021/03/04/Decentralized-content-moderation-system-for-Twitter</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://peterneugebauer.com/blockchain/2021/03/04/Decentralized-content-moderation-system-for-Twitter.html">&lt;p&gt;In this post I will try to lay out a proposal for a decentralized content moderation system for twitter, but it would work for any social media platform. I’m just using Twitter as an example here because I like it best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I will be referring to Twitter in this post I will also refer to a decentralized version of Twitter with its own native token, as it’s very hard to do a decentralized content moderation system it in a centralized platform, as you need a form of collateral (in this case twt tokens).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At a very abstract level, a Twitter is not much different form a democratic State; you have a bunch of parties with different motives and goals that exist in a given system which they have influence upon and that needs moderation and enforcement of rules to work properly. Because of these similarities I propose a system for content moderation that is very close to the judicial system of a state. In a traditional system (state) it’s “users” stake personal freedom and wealth, but of course you can’t do that in blockchain land, so we’re going to use twt tokens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;policy-enforcement&quot;&gt;Policy (enforcement)&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Easy policies. And when I say easy I mean easy; maybe up to 10 rules for the whole platform on how to behave, mostly common sense stuff (e.g. no death threads; be nice; etc.). The goal here is that literally everybody who uses the platform can understand all its rules and knows when he/she violates them. Here we have an advantage of decentralized platform, the policies are made by the people for other people to read not by lawyers for other lawyers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; Have a prosecutor, defender &amp;amp; judge system for policy violation: The process is as follows 1) prosecutor P sees a post by Defender D he thinks violates Twitters rules. He reports the post and stakes 100twt to back his report. 2) D gets a message his post has been flagged and can now a) also stake 100twt and go to court over if it’s a violation or b) accept the report, delete the post and get a small fine (and P gets a portion of that fine as a reward). 3) If he does oppose the report and stakes his 100twt the case gets send to a judge who then decides. The winner gets &amp;gt;50% of the combined stake pool, with fractions going to the judge and maybe a network handling fee. This punishes wrong behavior and while also discouraging filing reports for nothing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-judgesystem&quot;&gt;The Judge System&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One large Problem that remains is who are the Judges, who appoints them and how does the network protect itself against corrupt Judges. I propose a multi-layer Judge system as sketched out below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/twitter_judge_layers.png&quot; alt=&quot;title&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way the system works is that 1) every judge has to stake a rather substantial amount of twt to become a judge (with every layer/level judges having to stake substantially more than his predecessor), this is the only necessary prerequisite to become a judge and 2) there is an appeal process; if you think the judge handling your case ruled wrongly against you, you can stake a higher amount and appeal to a higher layer judge to look at the case. If that L2 judge decides in your favour and against the L1 judges ruling, the L1 Judge would lose his stake, thus promoting honest behavior. (It is still to be determined how high these stake amount need to be for the system to work best and not promote gambling while being accessible for people with lower twt balances.) If a L2 Judge overrules a L1 Judge, both the L1 Judge and the original prosecutor P can appeal again to a higher Layer Judge (in this case L3) to look at the issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process can of course not continue infinitely, so there is a supreme court as the highest institution of jurisdiction. This Supreme Court consists of multiple parties and is elected democratically by twt (or an equivalent) holders. Due to the nature of the System it is very improbable that many cases reach the SC, as it’s very expensive to stake all the twt necessary, should the SC rule in your favour though you would gain quite a lot, and it would (as in the real system) have consequences for how lower layer judges rule in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at an example to help understand the system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;P comes across a post by D stating “Jacks dead if I meet him”. He flags the post as a violation against the no death threads policy and stakes 100twt. D opposes the flag, and he also stakes 100twt, claiming it’s not a violation of the policy. The case gets send to JL1. JL1 decides in P’s favour and the trust, containing the 200twt, is to be split 70% to P, 20% to JL1 and 10% for the network treasury. D can now accept the judges ruling or stake 400 for a L2 judge to look at it, which he does. JL2 also decides in P’s favour and now the trust (containing 600twt) is split 50% for P, 15% for JL1, 25% for JL2 and 10% for the network. This time D accepts the ruling and the twt is paid out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The percentages in the example are also just exemplary. What is important however is that JL2 gets paid more than JL1, as he has a higher stake in the network.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="blockchain" /><summary type="html">In this post I will try to lay out a proposal for a decentralized content moderation system for twitter, but it would work for any social media platform. I’m just using Twitter as an example here because I like it best.</summary></entry></feed>